This video demonstrates how to perform
a distance and near visual acuity
test.
Wash your hands and don't PPE.
You will need the arclight charts and a safety pin to make pinholes.
The room must be quiet and at least three metres wide.
It should be well lit ideally with natural light.
If you're outside, make sure the sun is on the patient's back shining onto the chart.
The patient should be seated comfortably although standing is okay.
Show the patient the chart at arm's length, and ask them to point in
the direction at the
ease point.
Check the patient understands and you're both happy to start.
If the patient
normally wears glasses for distance, use them for the test.
If not, then test unaided.
They
should cover one eye with a pan with their hand, not their fingers.
Place the chart at
the same level as the patient's eyes at a distance of 3 metres.
Start with the largest letters at
the top of the chart working downwards.
Stop the test when the patient can no longer correctly
indicate the direction of the ease or they complete the test.
Now record the acuity achieved.
The left side of the chart is labelled in Snellin notation with log mar on the right.
Snellin
is recorded as a fraction with a test distance on top and the last
full line seen correctly
on the bottom.
If some of the next line was also seen then
right plus one, or plus two, for extra letters seen.
For a log mar again, record the last
full line read correctly, but this time subtract 0.07 if they managed one extra letter correctly,
or 0.14 if they saw two.
If the patient cannot see even the biggest E at 3 metres, then half
the distance to 1.5 metres.
If they still cannot see at this distance, then test if they can
count your fingers, follow your hand movements or if they can perceive light.
Record what
they could see and the distance.
If the patient's vision is reduced, less than 3 over 3 or
log mar 0, then also test with a pinhole.
This can show if the vision is reduced due to lack
of glasses.
You can make a set of pinholes by pushing a pin through the near card where
the black dots are.
As the patient to hold the card over the eye you are testing while
covering their other eye with their palm.
They will need to move it up or down a little
so they can see through at least one hole.
Repeat distance testing with the pinhole and
record the results, making it clear that this test was with a pinhole.
Now test near visual acuity.
Ask the patient to hold the chart 40cm away at a typical reading
angle.
If they own reading glasses test with them on.
If not, then test unaided.
Ask them
to keep both eyes open this time.
Explain that you want them to read out loud, starting with
the biggest letters at the top of the chart.
If the patient cannot read well, then ask them
to point to small words or certain letters such as O, name letters in
the words, match
letters to a matching card or copy the shapes of letters in the ear with their finger.
Stop
the test when the patient can no longer read accurately and comfortably.
Record the number
of the last line they saw clearly.
If their near vision is worse than N8, then repeat with
reading glasses of different powers.